Guide to the Nicola Chiaromonte Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1926-72; Series II; 3.5; (7 boxes)
  - MANUSCRIPTS
    - Drafts
      - Untitled manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 213-14)
      - Untitled typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 215-16)
    - Notes
      - Caffi, Andrea - "Peuple et raison d'état": typescript (Box 6, Folder 217)
      - Caffi, Andrea - notes: typescript, 1941-45, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 218-20)
      - "Justice" - miscellaneous notes: typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 221-22)
      - "Lenin - Stato I Rivoluzione" notes: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 223)
      - Notes on cinema: "Arnheim": typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 224)
      - Notes on cinema: "C.L. Ragghianti": manuscript, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 225)
      - Notes on cinema: typescript, carbon, 1961, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 226)
      - Notes on literature: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 227)
      - Notes on Toynbee: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 228)
      - "Politica" notes: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 229)
      - "Prisons d'Espagne": manuscript, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 230)
      - Notes - miscellaneous: manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 231-33)
      - Fragment re "Le Fondamenta della vita civile": typescript, corrected (Box 6, Folder 234)
      - Fragment re Sartre: typescript, carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 235)
      - Fragment re "La Società letteraria": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 236)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Bibliography of political writings, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 237)
    - Bibliography of writings on theater, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 238)
    - "Cacciatori di Leoni," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 Nov 12 (Box 7, Folder 239)
    - "Chiarimenti: Al Saggiatore e Amici," Oggi, 1933 Dec 24 (Box 7, Folder 240)
    - "Cinelandia," L'Italia Letteraria, [1932] (Box 7, Folder 241)
    - "Cinema," [Reviews] L'Italia Letteraria, 1933-34 (Box 7, Folder 242-44)
    - Come tu mi vuoi di Pirandello," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 Apr 23 (Box 7, Folder 245)
    - "Conrad, Il mare, L'ignoto," Conscientia, 1926 Nov 20 (Box 7, Folder 246)
    - "Contro Freud," La Stampa, 1933 Jan 10 (Box 7, Folder 247)
    - "La Corte dei complimenti," L'Interplanetario, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 248)
    - "Crisi e soluzione della modernità," Conscientia, 1926 Jun 19 (Box 7, Folder 249)
    - "Dall'attimo divino all'Eterno", 1926 sep 11 (Box 7, Folder 250)
    - "Del realismo scenographico," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 Dec 24 (Box 7, Folder 251)
    - "Dialogo sui piaceri collettivi," Oggi, 1933 Jul 23 (Box 7, Folder 252)
    - "Difesa della cultura," Oggi, 1934 Jan (Box 7, Folder 253)
    - "Diagnostica dei ventenni," Conscientia, 1926 Sep 25 (Box 7, Folder 254)
    - "L'estetica di Tilgher," Il Saggiatore, 1930 Dec (Box 7, Folder 255)
    - "Il familiare Wordsworth," L'Italia Letteraria, 1931 May 24 (Box 7, Folder 256)
    - "Fantasia di Stevenson," L'Italia Letteraria, 1931 Jun 14 (Box 7, Folder 257)
    - "Geografie," Il Saggiatore, 1930 Dec (Box 7, Folder 258)
    - "Glosse e motivi", 1926 Nov 13 (Box 7, Folder 259)
    - "Intorno ad un 'Pamphlet'," Il Mondo, 1936 Jun 18 (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - "Lawrence moralista," L'Italia Letteraria, 1931 Jul 12 (Box 7, Folder 261)
    - "Mamoulian o il gioco delle immagini," L'Italia Letteraria, 1932 Jun 19 (Box 7, Folder 262)
    - "Il millenovecento a Parigi," L'Italia Letteraria, 1932 Sep 4 (Box 7, Folder 263)
    - "Mimo di Cloe Pastorella", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 264)
    - "Morale della città," Conscientia, 1926 Oct 17 (Box 7, Folder 265)
    - "Il pittore Carlo Levi," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 Jan 22 (Box 7, Folder 266)
    - "Il problema della Filosofia del diritto in B. Croce," L'Idealismo Realistico", 1928 Jul 1 (Box 7, Folder 267)
    - "Profunda notte," L'Italia Letteraria, 1932 May 1 (Box 7, Folder 268)
    - "Rinascimento", 1926 Sep 29 (Box 7, Folder 269)
    - "Specillo dello spirito contemporaneo," Conscienta, 1926 Jun 26 (Box 7, Folder 270)
    - "Thomas Hardy, romanziere pessimista," L'Italia Letteraria, 1931 Nov 22 (Box 7, Folder 271)
    - "Tilgher e le morali del Novecento," Rivisti di Cultura, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 272)
    - "'Treno Popolare' al Barberini," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 Nov 12 (Box 7, Folder 273)
    - "Umanismo di G.W. Pabst," Scenario, 1932 Aug (Box 7, Folder 274)
    - "'Verso la vita': film educativo," Il Tevere, 1932 Jan 15 (Box 7, Folder 275)
    - " La Visione greca della vita di A. Tilgher" Il Mondo, 1926 May 5 (Box 7, Folder 276)
    - Settanta 23, 1972 Apr (Box 7, Folder 277)
  - THEATER REVIEWS
    - Vol. 1, 1953-54 (Box 8, Folder 278)
    - Vol. 2, 1954-55 (Box 8, Folder 279)
    - Vol. 2, 1955-56 (Box 8, Folder 280)
    - Vol. 3, 1957-58 (Box 8, Folder 281)
    - Vol. 4, 1959-60 (Box 8, Folder 282)
    - Vol. 4, 1960-61 (Box 8, Folder 283)
    - Vol. 5, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 284)
    - Vol. 5, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 285)
    - Vol. 6, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 286)
    - Vol. 6, 1965-66 (Box 9, Folder 287)
    - Vol. 7, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 288)
    - Vol. 7, 1967-68 (Box 9, Folder 289)
    - Vol. 8, 1968-69 (Box 10, Folder 290)
    - Vol. 8, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 291)
    - Vol. 9, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 292)
    - Vol. 9, 1971-72 (Box 10, Folder 293)
- Writings by Others, 1933-64; Series III; 0.25; (0.5 boxes)
  Series III, Writings by Others, is arranged alphabetically by author. Works with multiple authors and anonymous works are filed at the end of the series by title.
  - Carella, Domenico: "Chiarimenti: a Nicola e amici," Oggi, 1933 Dec 31 (Box 11, Folder 294)
  - Carella, Domenico: "In margine all'inchiesta del 'Saggiatore'," Oggi, 1933 Dec 17 (Box 11, Folder 295)
  - Consiglio, Alberto: "Problemi del cinematografo," L'Italia Letteraria, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 296)
  - MacDonald, Dwight: comments on "Remarks on Justice": typescript, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 297)
  - Moravia, Alberto: "Il Chirurgo dietro l'obbiettivo", 1964 Jun 12 (Box 11, Folder 298)
  - [Simero]: "Fascismo e intelligenza", 1934 Dec (Box 11, Folder 299)
  - Tilgher, Adriano: Homo Faber, review article, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 300)
  - Giustizia e Libertà, 1932 Mar (Box 11, Folder 301)
  - "A Tribute to Nicola Chiaromonte", 1982 (Box 11, Folder 302)
- Personal Papers, 1923-71; Series IV; 3.5; (6.5 boxes)
  Series IV, Personal Papers, consists entirely of manuscript notebooks which Chiaromonte kept over many years. Some were given a title by Chiaromonte corresponding to their content (listed here in parentheses); beginning in 1955, the notebooks were also numbered sequentially. The notebooks are organized by date; undated items are at the end of the series.
  - Notebook, 1923-24 (Box 11, Folder 303)
  - Notebook, 1924 Jan-Dec (Box 11, Folder 304)
  - Notebook, 1925 Jan-Apr (Box 11, Folder 305)
  - Notebook, 1925-26 (Box 11, Folder 306)
  - Notebook, 1927 Feb-Mar (Box 11, Folder 307)
  - Notebook, [1930] (Box 11, Folder 308)
  - Notebook, 1930 Nov (Box 11, Folder 309)
  - Notebook (Parigi, Roma), 1932 May-Sep (Box 11, Folder 310)
  - Notebook (Roma), 1932-33 (Box 12, Folder 311)
  - Notebook (Flight From Paris), 1940-41 (Box 12, Folder 312)
  - Notebook (Pécharidle, Whitehead), 1940-41 (Box 12, Folder 313)
  - Notebook, 1943 Aug-Sep (Box 12, Folder 314)
  - Notebook (Truro, New York), 1945-46 (Box 12, Folder 315)
  - Notebook (Ischia, Napoli, Pompei, Vesuvio), 1947 Jul-Aug (Box 12, Folder 316)
  - Notebook (New York), 1947 Sep (Box 12, Folder 317)
  - Notebook (Paris), 1949 Apr-May (Box 12, Folder 318)
  - Notebook, 1951 Jul (Box 12, Folder 319)
  - Notebook (Paris), 1951 Sep (Box 12, Folder 320)
  - Notebook (Quercianella, Paris), 1952-53 (Box 12, Folder 321)
  - Notebook (New York, Paris), 1952-53 (Box 12, Folder 322)
  - Notebook (Paris), 1955 Jan (Box 12, Folder 323)
  - Notebook 1, 1955 Oct (Box 13, Folder 324)
  - Notebook 2, 1955 Oct (Box 13, Folder 325)
  - Notebook 3, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 326)
  - Notebook 4, 1958-60 (Box 13, Folder 327)
  - Notebook 5, 1960-61 (Box 13, Folder 328)
  - Notebook 6, 1961 May-Sep (Box 13, Folder 329)
  - Notebook 7, 1961 Oct-Dec (Box 13, Folder 330)
  - Notebook 8, 1961-62 (Box 13, Folder 331)
  - Notebook 9, 1962 Jun-Sep (Box 13, Folder 332)
  - Notebook 10, 1962 Oct (Box 13, Folder 333)
  - Notebook 11, 1962 Nov-Dec (Box 13, Folder 334)
  - Notebook 12, 1962-63 (Box 13, Folder 335)
  - Notebook 13, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 336)
  - Notebook 14, 1963 Jul-Aug (Box 13, Folder 337)
  - Notebook 15, 1963 Sep (Box 14, Folder 338)
  - Notebook 16, 1963 Oct (Box 14, Folder 339)
  - Notebook 17, 1963 Nov-Dec (Box 14, Folder 340)
  - Notebook 18, 1963-64 (Box 14, Folder 341)
  - Notebook 19, 1964 Jan-Feb (Box 14, Folder 342)
  - Notebook 20, 1964 Feb-Mar (Box 14, Folder 343)
  - Notebook 21, 1964 Mar-Apr (Box 14, Folder 344)
  - Notebook 22, 1964 Apr-May (Box 14, Folder 345)
  - Notebook 23, 1964 May (Box 14, Folder 346)
  - Notebook 24, 1964 Jun (Box 14, Folder 347)
  - Notebook 25, 1964 Jul-Aug (Box 14, Folder 348)
  - Notebook 26, 1964 Aug-Sep (Box 14, Folder 349)
  - Notebook 27, 1964 Sep-Oct (Box 14, Folder 350)
  - Notebook 28, 1964 Oct-Nov (Box 14, Folder 351)
  - Notebook 29, 1964-65 (Box 15, Folder 352)
  - Notebook 30, 1965 Feb-Mar (Box 15, Folder 353)
  - Notebook 31, 1965 Mar-May (Box 15, Folder 354)
  - Notebook 32, 1965 Jun-Aug (Box 15, Folder 355)
  - Notebook 33, 1965 Aug-Sep (Box 15, Folder 356)
  - Notebook 34, 1965 Sep-Nov (Box 15, Folder 357)
  - Notebook 35, 1965-66 (Box 15, Folder 358)
  - Notebook 36, 1966 Mar-Oct (Box 15, Folder 359)
  - Notebook 37, 1967 Jan-Apr (Box 15, Folder 360)
  - Notebook 38, 1967 Apr-Jun (Box 15, Folder 361)
  - Notebook 39, 1967 Jun-Aug (Box 15, Folder 362)
  - Notebook 40, 1967 Sep-Oct (Box 15, Folder 363)
  - Notebook 41, 1967 Oct-Dec (Box 16, Folder 364)
  - Notebook 42, 1968 Jan-Mar (Box 16, Folder 365)
  - Notebook 43, 1968 Apr-Jul (Box 16, Folder 366)
  - Notebook 44, 1968 Mar-Jul (Box 16, Folder 367)
  - Notebook 45, 1968-69 (Box 16, Folder 368)
  - Notebook 46, 1969 Jan-Apr (Box 16, Folder 369)
  - Notebook 47, 1969 May-Aug (Box 16, Folder 370)
  - Notebook 48, 1969 Aug-Nov (Box 16, Folder 371)
  - Notebook 49, 1969 Nov (Box 16, Folder 372)
  - Notebook 50, 1970 Mar-Apr (Box 16, Folder 373)
  - Notebook 51, 1970 Jun-Dec (Box 16, Folder 374)
  - Notebook 52, 1971 Jan-Jun (Box 17, Folder 375)
  - Notebook 53, 1971 Jun-Sep (Box 17, Folder 376)
  - Notebook (Moira), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 377)
  - Notebook (Movies), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 378)
  - Notebook (Movie, Malraux, Saint Just), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 379)
  - Notebook (Proudhon, Leibniz, Berthelot), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 380)
  - Notebook (Husserl, Proudhon), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 381)
- Oversize (1 box), n.d.
  - Photographs of columns from Giustizia e Libertà, 1934-35, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 382)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 19: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 23 (Box 19, Folder 383)
  - Box 2, folder 29 (Box 19, Folder 384)
  - Box 2, folder 50 (Box 19, Folder 385)
  - Box 2, folder 59 (Box 19, Folder 386)
  - Box 2, folder 60 (Box 19, Folder 387)
  - Box 2, folder 79 (Box 19, Folder 388)
  - Box 2, folder 80 (Box 19, Folder 389)
  - Box 2, folder 95 (Box 19, Folder 390)
  - Box 4, folder 104 (Box 19, Folder 391)
  - Box 4, folder 105 (Box 19, Folder 392)
  - Box 4, folder 109 (Box 19, Folder 393)
  - Box 4, folder 111 (Box 19, Folder 394)
  - Box 4, folder 114 (Box 19, Folder 395)
  - Box 4, folder 119 (Box 19, Folder 396)
  - Box 4, folder 126 (Box 19, Folder 397)
  - Box 4, folder 130 (Box 19, Folder 398)
  - Box 4, folder 135 (Box 19, Folder 399)
  - Box 5, folder 156 (Box 19, Folder 400)
  - Box 5, folder 159 (Box 19, Folder 401)
  - Box 5, folder 165 (Box 19, Folder 402)
  - Box 5, folder 166 (Box 19, Folder 403)
  - Box 5, folder 178 (Box 19, Folder 404)
  - Box 5, folder 189 (Box 19, Folder 405)
  - Box 5, folder 203 (Box 19, Folder 406)
  - Box 5, folder 204 (Box 19, Folder 407)
  - Box 6, folder 213 (Box 19, Folder 408)
  - Box 6, folder 214 (Box 19, Folder 409)
  - Box 6, folder 216 (Box 19, Folder 410)
  - Box 6, folder 219 (Box 19, Folder 411)
  - Box 6, folder 221 (Box 19, Folder 412)
  - Box 6, folder 222 (Box 19, Folder 413)
  - Box 6, folder 227 (Box 19, Folder 414)
  - Box 6, folder 229 (Box 19, Folder 415)
  - Box 6, folder 230 (Box 19, Folder 416)
  - Box 7, folder 239 (Box 19, Folder 417)
  - Box 7, folder 242 (Box 19, Folder 418)
  - Box 7, folder 243 (Box 19, Folder 419)
  - Box 7, folder 244 (Box 19, Folder 420)
  - Box 7, folder 261 (Box 19, Folder 421)
  - Box 7, folder 263 (Box 19, Folder 422)
  - Box 7, folder 266 (Box 19, Folder 423)
  - Box 7, folder 271 (Box 19, Folder 424)